Guide to the New York City COVID-19 Food Studies Web Collection MSS.607
Fales Library and Special Collections
New York City COVID-19 Food Studies Web Collection
September 2020-ongoing
Fales Library and Special Collections
James Beard Foundation
Soul Fire Farm
Village Alliance (New York, N.Y.)
The Street Vendor Project
New York University
Minetta Creek Collective
Kumar, Thiru
Black Feminist Project
Black Chef Movement
Bentley, Amy, 1962-
32BJ Service Employees International Union
Tsai, Moonlynn
MSS.607
53 websites in 53 archived websites.
New York City COVID-19 Food Studies Web Collection is made of archived websites that detail the impact on COVID-19 on food communities in New York City and at New York University, beginning in 2020.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Websites were selected by curators Jasmine Sykes-Kunk, Janet Bunde, Michael Koncewicz, Shannon O'Neill, Nicholas Martin and web archivist Nicole Greenhouse through the use of Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. The accession numbers associated with these websites are 2021.034, 2021.035, 2021.036, 2021.037, 2022.030, 2022.042, and 2023.062.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Facebook was inconsistently captured due to crawling technology limitations.
Google Drive documents were captured but do not playback.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Appraisal
Robots.txt (a piece of code designed to limit crawler activity within a website) was ignored. Unless noted, the collection was rescoped to allow for Google documents and videos embedded in the website.
Arrangement
Websites are arranged alphabetically by creator.
Scope and Contents
New York City COVID-19 Food Studies Web Collection is made of archived websites that detail the impact on COVID-19 on food communities in New York City. It documents the effects of the pandemic on New York University's campuses and their surrounding food communities, their shifts in cultural, economic, and social practices around the city, and their organizing and response efforts, with an intentional focus on Black and Indigenous People of Color, Asian American Pacific Islander, and LGBTQIA+ communities.
Food communities documented in the collection consist of food workers, farms and their workers, food non-profits, food vendors, farmers' markets, private and community gardens, alternative food sources, mutual aid networks, community refrigerators and food pantries, restaurants, and soup kitchens. The collection focuses on issues of food justice and food scarcity through a lens of race and class. within NYU's staff and students and in the greater New York City community.
Historical Note
In March 2020, non-essential businesses throughout New York City closed in an effort to contain COVID-19, a respiratory virus that first identified in December 2019. The virus and the closures disproportionally affected systematically excluded groups, such as Black, Indigenous, and People of Color, Asian American Pacific Islander, and LGBTQIA+ communities. Restaurants and other public venues were closed to indoor dining and could only offer delivery and take-out; later many closed permanently. Chinatown restaurants were harshly affected, not only due to closures, but due to an increase in anti-Asian racism and xenophobia. Street vendors also suffered, due to lack of commuters and minimal protections. Early in the pandemic, restaurants also provided free meals to essential workers and other food workers changed their business models to remain in business. In late March 2020, Congress passed the CARES Act (Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security Act) which, in addition to other government assistance, helped keep restaurants and small businesses open.
Closures also led to unemployment, which increased the need for food aid programs. Both governmental and mutual aid food programs sprung up to assist food insecurity, especially for children who depended on school meals and Black, Lantine, and immigrant communities whose food insecurity was excerabated by the pandemic. The NYU community also provided courtesy meal programs for food insecure students and quarantining and isolating students.
Summer 2020 also led to the expansion of outdoor dining as part of the New York City reopening program. Indoor dining returned in August 2020, which led to debate between the financial needs of businesses and minimizing the spread of COVID-19. In 2022, vaccine requirements led to conflict between diners and restaurants. As of this writing in June 2022, the pandemic is still an active part of life.
Food security.; Food habits -- New York (State) -- New York; Restaurants.; COVID-19 (Disease); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Farming; Agricultural education.; Street vendors
- My Fastfood Story, September 2020-ongoing; 32BJ Service Employees International Union (Box Electronic Records)
  Scope and Contents
  32BJ SEIU's page that collects stories from workers across the fast food industry in NYC. The site includes a section that focuses on Chipotle and their history of worker abuses. The website includes photographs, a blog with worker testimonies, and ongoing campaign updates in the form of a news section.
- Just Cause Laws Video, August 2022; 32BJ Service Employees International Union (Box Electronic Records)
  Explainer video detailing the Just Cause laws that protect New York City's 70,000 fast-food workers from unfair firings, hour reductions, and wage cuts.
- Serving Up Justice Twitter, September 2020-April 2022; 32BJ Service Employees International Union (Box Electronic Records)
  Twitter account documenting 32BJ SEIU's fast food restaurant workers.
- Food and COVID-19 NYC Digital Archive and Collection, March 2022; Bentley, Amy, 1962- (Box Electronic Records)
  The Food and COVID-19 NYC Archive is a curated digital collection of materials, photos, personal narratives, menus, media articles and more, began in the spring of 2020 as a NYU food studies graduate seminar class project, and evolved into a space capturing the food experiences of New Yorkers as they navigated the traumas of the COVID-19 pandemic through 2020 and into the spring of 2021. While the ongoing pandemic will affect NYC food for years, this archive documents a full year, from March 2020 through March 2021. Following the ebbs and flows of the pandemic's intensity, the site captures the landscape of food topically (food insecurity, restaurants, shopping, and at home) as well as chronologically. The project also provides links to other collections and related articles.
- NYC's Chinatown Through COVID, March-May 2022; Bentley, Amy, 1962- (Box Electronic Records)
  Part of the Food and COVID-19 NYC Digital Archive and Collection. This website explores some of the challenges uniquely faced by businesses in NYC's Chinatown during the first nine months of the coronavirus pandemic by Liana Kindler.
- Stockpiling During COVID-19, March-April 2022; Bentley, Amy, 1962- (Box Electronic Records)
  Part of the Food and COVID-19 NYC Digital Archive and Collection. This website examines stockpiling and other grocery trends that took place during the COVID-19 pandemic by Kayla Nelson.
- What's For Dinner?, March-April 2022; Bentley, Amy, 1962- (Box Electronic Records)
  Part of the Food and COVID-19 NYC Digital Archive and Collection. "What's for Dinner?", was a personal investigation of COVID-19's impact on feeding work in New York City by Daisy Zeijlon. This timeline chronicles the weekly meal plans I made from March 21, 2020 - November 20, 2020, intersecting them with important pandemic moments: high and low positive test and death rates, grocery store shortages and phases of reopening, amongst other milestones. This project's purpose is to demonstrate the ways that the public narrative surrounding COVID-19 in NYC and the private experience of living through it overlap, contrast and interact.
- Black Chef Movement, September 2020-ongoing (Box Electronic Records)
  "Black Chef Movement supports justice for Black and brown communities through the preparation and distribution of nutritious meals to people fighting for change, whether that is at a protest, at the voting booth, or in healthcare. We provide stipends to underemployed food industry workers and use our platform to uplift the work of Black and brown chefs." This website acts as a foundation for the Black Chef Movement's work: it provides links to ways that individuals can participate in their work through volunteering or donations, and it links to the Black Chef Movement's social media which documents their daily activity. The Black Chef Movement's website includes a calendar that indicates when and where they will be offering free food to on-the-ground activists, movement workers, or anyone in need of a meal.
- Black Chef Movement Facebook, September 2020-ongoing; Black Chef Movement (Box Electronic Records)
  The Facebook page of the Black Chef Movement documents the daily activities of the organization, including when and where they will be set up to feed on-the-ground activists, movement workers, and anyone in need of a meal. It is also where the organization makes calls for volunteer support and where they document via photos and video their actions. The Facebook also highlights Black chefs who are participating in the movement through the use of profiles.
- Black Feminist Project, September 2020-ongoing (Box Electronic Records)
  "The Black Feminist Project enriches the lives of, restores agency, justice, joy, and health to Black Womxn, girls, and non-men, often referred to as marginalized genders or MaGes and the children they care for - with an emphasis on mother-led families." The Black Feminist Project operates several on-going projects including the Black Joy Farm, a "radical food growing green space in the South Bronx;" a food pantry program, a dinner series, and fundraising campaigns.
- James Beard Foundation: A Message About COVID-19, September 2020-March 2021; James Beard Foundation (Box Electronic Records)
  This webpage lists resources and toolkits available to restaurant owners and operators. The page also mentions a newsletter.
- COVID-19 Advocacy Toolkit, October 2020-March 2021; James Beard Foundation (Box Electronic Records)
  Part of the Chef Advocacy Toolkit put together by the James Beard Foundation.
- Restaurants employ 16 million Americans Infographic, October 2020-March 2021; James Beard Foundation (Box Electronic Records)
- Nearly $900 billion in restaurant sales in 2019 Infographic, October 2020-March 2021; James Beard Foundation (Box Electronic Records)
- Save Restaurants. Call Congress. Infographic, October 2020-March 2021; James Beard Foundation (Box Electronic Records)
- Save Restaurants Infographic, October 2020-March 2021; James Beard Foundation (Box Electronic Records)
- Independent Restaurant Coalition Social Toolkit, October 2020-March 2021; James Beard Foundation (Box Electronic Records)
- Sample Save Restaurants Social Media, October 2020-March 2021; James Beard Foundation (Box Electronic Records)
- COVID-19 Resources: NRA and SBA (National Restaurant Association and Small Business Association), October 2020-March 2021; James Beard Foundation (Box Electronic Records)
- State-By-State Statistics from National Restaurant Association (NRA), October 2020-March 2021; James Beard Foundation (Box Electronic Records)
- Members of Congress Social Media Handles, October 2020-March 2021; James Beard Foundation (Box Electronic Records)
- Talking Points for your Member of Congress, October 2020-March 2021; James Beard Foundation (Box Electronic Records)
- How Congress can help independent restaurants Letter, October 2020-March 2021; James Beard Foundation (Box Electronic Records)
- NY Dosa Twitter, September 2020-ongoing; Kumar, Thiru (Box Electronic Records)
  This is the twitter feed for the NY Dosa cart, ran by Thiru Kumar, in Washington Square Park
- Minetta Creek Collective, November 2021-ongoing (Box Electronic Records)
  Minetta Creek Collective organization seeks to connect members of the Washington Square Park community with free food, classes, and events, and runs a free farmstand on Wednesdays.
- Food Security at NYU, March 2021; Murphy, Bridget; Parekh, Niyati (Box Electronic Records)
  This article details research conducted by affiliates of the Institute of Human Development and Social Change at Steinhardt.
- Food Insecurity Resources, March 2021; New York University (Box Electronic Records)
  Resources at NYU and beyond, collated by the Department of History, offering resources for NYU students experiencing food insecurity.
- Creative Kitchen: Recipes for Families to Fuel Their Body and Mind, March 2021; New York University (Box Electronic Records)
  This cookbook represents a collaboration between students in the Department of Art and Art Professions and the Department of Nutrition and Food Studies at the Steinhardt School of Culture, Education and Human Development. The cookbook, which is intended to provide healthy, low-cost recipes and art activities to bring families together, was distributed to NYC public schools in 2020.
- NYU Courtesy Meals, March 2021-ongoing; New York University (Box Electronic Records)
  This page describes the courtesy meal program for students experiencing food insecurity at NYU.
- NYU Eats Twitter, March 2021-ongoing; New York University (Box Electronic Records)
  This account includes social media content from NYU Eats.
- Dining on Campus, March 2021-ongoing; New York University (Box Electronic Records)
  This page describes dining options available to NYU students on campus through NYU Eats, which is a collaboration between the University and the vendor Chartwells.
- Soul Fire Farm, September 2020-ongoing (Box Electronic Records)
  "Soul Fire Farm is a BIPOC-centered community farm committed to ending racism and injustice in the food system." The Soul Fire Website acts as a place where the collective shares resources, programming, and more to introduce visitors to the work that they do. It includes videos, linked Google Docs, and an online newsletter.
- Soul Fire Farm Twitter, September 2020-ongoing; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
  "Soul Fire Farm is a BIPOC-centered community farm committed to ending racism and injustice in the food system." The Soul Fire Twitter Account documents Soul Fire's daily activities and connections with various food justice communities. It regularly addresses issues of food scarcity, white supremacy and racism in foodways and food systems, labor issues for farmworkers, and food sovereignty.
- Soul Fire Farm Youtube Channel, November 2020-September 2023; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
  The Soul Fire Farm Youtube Channel contains videos from their Liberation on Land series and other videos from the Farm.
- Soul Fire Farm Youtube Channel, November 2023-ongoing; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
  The Soul Fire Farm Youtube Channel contains videos from their Liberation on Land series, indigenous farming practices, herbal medicine, recipes, food justice, cultivation, soil carbon, beekeeping, poultry raising, and other farming practices.
- Farming While Black, October 2020-March 2021; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
  Website for Soul Fire Farm's book, Farming While Black, a manual for African-heritage people to reclaim agency in the food system through farming.
- Sowing the Seeds of Food Justice, September 2020-March 2021; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
  Google document linked from the Soul Fire Farm website.
- Soul Fire Farm Building Immersion, September 2020-September 2021; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
- COVID-19 Press Release, September 2020-September 2021; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
- Community Farm Day FAQ, September 2020-September 2021; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
- Youth & Intergenerational Program FAQ, September 2020-September 2021; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
- How to Use Soul Fire Farm Materials with Integrity, September 2020-September 2021; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
- Living and Learning in Oaxaca, September 2020-March 2021; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
- Soul Fire Farm Language Justice Guide, September 2020-September 2021; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
- Inmersión Agrícola Soul Fire, September 2020-March 2021; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
- The Soul Fire Farming Immersion, September 2020-September 2021; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
- Soul Fire in the City Lawn to Garden Guide, September 2020-September 2021; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
- Accommodations Near Soul Fire Farm, September 2020-September 2021; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
- BIPOC Speakers - White Audiences: A Soul Fire Farm Guide to a Successful Collaboration, September 2020-March 2021; Soul Fire Farm (Box Electronic Records)
- The Street Vendor Project, September 2020-March 2021 (Box Electronic Records)
  "The Street Vendor Project is a membership-based project with more than 1,800 active vendor members who are working together to create a vendors' movement for permanent change. We reach out to vendors in the streets and storage garages and teach them about their legal rights and responsibilities." This website documents the work of the Street Vendor project, inclusive of their on-going campaigns, reports they've produced detailing the conditions of street vendors' works and lives, and their annual award (the Vendys), and a semi-regularly updated blog which provides more narrative and analysis.
- The Street Vendor Project Twitter, September 2020-ongoing; The Street Vendor Project (Box Electronic Records)
  The Twitter account for the Street Vendor Project provides more regular updates on their day-to-day work, their solidarity with other service industry workers, the work and condition of street vendors during the global pandemic crisis, and actions of street vendors to support individuals facing food scarcity during COVID-19.
- Heart of Dinner, September 2020-ongoing; Tsai, Moonlynn (Box Electronic Records)
  This website documents the efforts of Heart of Dinner, an organization cofounded by Ying Chang and Moonlyn Tsai. Heart of Dinner is an extension of #LOVINGCHINATOWN, launched by Chang and Tsai in response to COVID-19 "to counter the racism and isolation the Asian-American immigrant elderly have been experiencing throughout the pandemic." Heart of Dinner works with restaurant partners to provide meals and care packages to communities members facing food scarcity and isolation as a result of the COVID-19 global pandemic. The website includes a short video documentary, photos of community members, calls to action including requests to support the organization's GoFundMe and requests for individuals to send notes and decorate bags for community members.
- Village Alliance List of All Businesses and Operating Status, October 2020-ongoing; Village Alliance (New York, N.Y.) (Box Electronic Records)
  This Google sheet lists Greenwich Village businesses that are operating, along with a list of links to their websites.